Williams Obstetrics.
Chapter 49: General Considerations and Maternal.
Evaluation Medications.
Nonobstetrical Surgery.
Laparoscopic Surgery.
Radiography.
Diagnostic Radiation.
Sonography.
Magnetic Resonance Imaging.
References.
Pregnant women are susceptible to any medical and surgical disorder that can affect women of childbearing age.
Chronic illnesses often precede pregnancy, and an acute condition can complicate an otherwise normal pregnancy.
Both chronic and acute disorders raise the risk for antepartum hospitalization.
Approximately 10 per 100 pregnant women incur an antepartum admission, and one third are for nonobstetrical conditions that include renal, pulmonary, and infectious diseases .
The hospitalization rate due to trauma approximates 4 admissions per 1000 deliveries .
Those with intellectual and developmental disabilities have a higher incidence of hospitalization .
Last, 1 to 2 percent of pregnant women will undergo a nonobstetrical surgical procedure .
Obstetricians should have a working knowledge of the wide-ranging medical disorders common to childbearing-aged women.
Many of these are within the purview of the general obstetrician.
Other disorders, however, will warrant consultation with specialists in maternal-fetal medicine, and still others require a multidisciplinary team.
The latter may include internists and medical subspecialists, surgeons, and anesthesiologists .
The Society for Maternal-Fetal Medicine (2014) has redefined aspects of maternal care and proposed conditions requiring specialized care.
Treatment should never be withheld because a woman is pregnant.
To ensure this and allow for individualized care, several questions must be addressed: • What management would be recommended if the woman were not pregnant?
If the proposed management is different because the woman is pregnant, can this be justified?
What are the risks and benefits to the mother and her fetus, and are they counter to each other?
Can an individualized management plan be devised that balances risks versus benefits?
Maternal Physiology And Laboratory.
Values.
Pregnancy induces physiological changes in virtually all organ systems.
Many of these are discussed in Chapter 4 and in the subsequent chapters in this section.
In turn, numerous laboratory test results also are normally altered.
Some values would be considered abnormal in the nonpregnant woman.
Conversely, some may appear to be within a normal range but are decidedly abnormal for the gravida.
These changes may complicate the evaluation of coexisting conditions.
To aid interpretation, normal laboratory values in pregnancy are listed in the Appendix (p. 1227).
Medications.
Fortunately, most medications needed to treat frequently encountered illnesses in pregnancy can be given with relative safety .
That said, notable exceptions are considered in Chapter 8 and throughout this text.
The risks and benefits of medication use during pregnancy and lactation are outlined in drug labels using the Pregnancy and Lactation Labeling Rule (PLLR) requirement from the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA).
Nonobstetrical Surgery.
The chances of adverse maternal and perinatal outcomes following nonobstetrical surgery during pregnancy are relatively low and cannot be separated from risks of the underlying condition .
However, risks are likely greater with complications.
Compared with simple appendicitis, perforated appendicitis with feculent peritonitis has significantly higher maternal and perinatal morbidity and mortality rates even if surgical and anesthetic techniques are flawless.
Moreover, procedurerelated complications may adversely affect outcomes.
For example, a woman who has uncomplicated removal of an inflamed appendix may suffer aspiration of acidic gastric contents during tracheal intubation or extubation.
# Maternal Morbidity.
The most frequent nonobstetrical surgical procedures performed during pregnancy are appendectomy, cholecystectomy, and adnexal surgery (Vujic, 2019; Yu, 2018).
Postoperative complications in nonpregnant patients can similarly harm
gravid women.
However, data comparing these complications in these two groups are conflicting.
The National Surgical Quality Improvement Program showed that morbidity and mortality rates from nonobstetrical surgery did not differ between pregnant and nonpregnant women .
In a Taiwanese cohort of nearly 5600 gravidas, the infectious postoperative complication rate was slightly higher and the mortality rate was fourfold greater than those rates in nonpregnant women .
The reported postoperative complication rate in gravidas approximates 5 percent, and the maternal mortality rate in these cases is <1 percent (Huang, 2016; Vujic, 2019).
Moreover, preoperative infection, specifically sepsis, is associated with a higher risk of maternal death .
# Perinatal Morbidity.
Excessive perinatal morbidity associated with nonobstetrical surgery is also attributable in many cases to the disease itself rather than to surgery and anesthesia.
Two- to threefold elevated risks for spontaneous abortion, preterm delivery, preeclampsia, and cesarean delivery have been reported .
Balinskaite and associates (2017) identified a greater risk of fetal death, preterm birth, fetal-growth restriction, and cesarean delivery in 47,628 women undergoing nonobstetrical surgery.
Most of these complications developed in cases performed emergently .
The Swedish Birth Registry provides valuable data comparing perinatal outcomes in women undergoing surgery with those of the general obstetrical population .
The incidences of congenital malformations and stillbirth were not significantly different from those of nonexposed newborns.
However, incidences of low birthweight, preterm birth, and neonatal death were significantly higher.
Increased neonatal death rates were largely due to prematurity.
Table 49-1.
Birth Outcomes in 5405 Pregnant Women Undergoing Nonobstetrical Surgery Fetal abnormality rates are not associated with maternal surgery in early pregnancy.
Källén and Mazze (1990) reported a nonsignificant relationship between elevated neural-tube defect rates and operations performed at 4 to 5 weeks’ gestation.
A large database study found no evidence that anesthetic agents were teratogenic .
According to Briggs and coworkers (2017), most inhalation anesthetic agents appear safe.
More recently, concerns of neurodevelopmental harm with the use of anesthetics for obstetrical or fetal surgery have been raised.
In 2016, the FDA issued a warning regarding impaired brain development in children following in utero exposure to inhaled isoflurane, sevoflurane, and desflurane as well as intravenous propofol and midazolam.
Such risks appear to accrue after 3 hours or more of exposure .
Laparoscopic Surgery.
In the first trimester, laparoscopy is the most common procedure used for diagnosis and management of several surgical disorders.
In 2017, the Society of American Gastrointestinal and Endoscopic Surgeons (SAGES) updated its recommendations concerning laparoscopy use in pregnant women .
Table 49-2.
Some Guidelines from the Society of American Gastrointestinal Endoscopic Surgeons (SAGES) for Laparoscopic Surgery in Pregnant Women For pregnancy in general, laparotomy also is common.
One 5-year study of almost 1300 pregnant women reported that open appendectomy was performed in 36 percent of 857 gravidas compared with only 17 percent of nonpregnant patients.
Of those undergoing cholecystectomy, an open approach was used in 10 percent of 436 pregnant women compared with 5 percent of nonpregnant women .
In a study from Japan, Shigemi and colleagues (2019) described 6018 pregnant women undergoing abdominal surgery—4047 by laparotomy and 1971 by laparoscopy.
Operative times, hospital stay lengths, and rates of adverse fetal events and blood transfusion were all greater in the laparotomy group .
Others instead report equally satisfactory outcomes with either approach (Cox, 2016; Lee, 2019).
Randomized trials to compare benefits and risks of laparoscopy versus laparotomy during pregnancy are needed, but implementation seems unfeasible (Bunyavejchevin, 2013; Lee, 2019).
Table 49-3.
Comparative Outcomes in Pregnant Women Undergoing Abdominal Surgery For adnexal mass surgery in pregnancy, laparoscopy is preferred, and several studies confirm its relative safety (Daykan, 2016; Webb, 2015).
In addition, laparoscopic splenectomy, adrenalectomy, and nephrectomy also have been described in pregnant women (Asizare, 2014; Dong, 2014; Miller, 2012).
When first used, 26 to 28 weeks became the upper gestational-age limit recommended.
However, as experience has accrued, many now describe laparoscopic surgery performed in the third trimester .
In one report, a third of gravidas undergoing laparoscopic cholecystectomy or appendectomy were >26 weeks’ gestation .
No serious adverse sequelae are linked to these procedures, and laparoscopy can safely be performed in all trimesters.
# Hemodynamic Effects.
Precise effects of laparoscopy in the human fetus are unknown, but animal investigations are informative.
During laparoscopy, required abdominal insufflation causes hemodynamic changes that are summarized in Table 49-4.
Reedy and associates (1995) studied baboons at the human equivalent of 22 to 26 weeks’ gestation.
No substantive physiological changes were found with insufflation pressures of 10 mm Hg, but 20 mm Hg caused significant maternal cardiovascular and respiratory changes after 20 minutes.
These included faster respiratory rate, respiratory acidosis, diminished cardiac output, and increased pulmonary artery and capillary wedge pressures.
In pregnant ewes, uteroplacental blood flow declines when intraperitoneal insufflation pressure exceeded 15 mm Hg (Barnard, 1995; Hunter, 1995).
This stemmed from decreased perfusion pressure and elevated placental vessel resistance .
Table 49-4.
Physiological Effects of CO2 Insufflation of the Peritoneal Cavity In women, cardiorespiratory changes are generally not severe if insufflation pressures remain <15 mm Hg.
Despite maintaining these low insufflation pressures in women at midpregnancy, the cardiac index dropped 26 percent after 5 minutes of insufflation and 21 percent after 15 minutes .
Even so, mean arterial pressures, systemic vascular resistance, and heart rate did not change significantly.
# Technique.
The following is an overview of laparoscopic technique in pregnancy.
For a detailed description and illustrations refer to Chapter 15 in Cunningham and Gilstrap’s Operative Obstetrics, 3rd edition .
Preparation for laparoscopy differs little from that used for laparotomy.
Bowel cleansing is not needed but may aid visualization and manipulations by emptying the colon.
Nasogastric or orogastric decompression reduces the risk of stomach trocar puncture and aspiration.
Aortocaval compression is avoided by a left-lateral tilt of the patient’s body.
Positioning of the lower extremities in boot-type stirrups maintains access to the vagina for fetal sonographic assessment or manual uterine displacement.
Intrauterine manipulators are logically avoided.
Pregnancy-related hypercoagulability combined with pneumoperitoneum-associated, lower-extremity venous stasis raises venous thromboembolism risks.
Prophylactic pneumatic compression devices are wrapped around the calves during patient positioning.
Most reports describe the use of general endotracheal anesthesia with monitoring of end-tidal carbon dioxide—EtCO2 (Hong, 2006; Ribic-Pucelj, 2007).
With controlled ventilation, EtCO2 is maintained between 30 and 35 mm Hg.
Beyond the first trimester, technical modifications of standard pelvic laparoscopic entry are required to avoid uterine puncture or laceration .
Many recommend open entry techniques to avoid perforations of the uterus, pelvic vessels, and adnexa.
With the method described by Hasson (1971, 1974), the abdomen is incised at or above the umbilicus, and the peritoneal cavity entered under direct visualization .
At this point, the cannula is connected to the insufflation system, and a 12–mm Hg pneumoperitoneum is created.
The initial insufflation should be conducted slowly to allow for prompt assessment and reversal of any untoward
pressure-related effects.
Gas leakage around the cannula is managed by tightening the surrounding skin with a towel clamp.
Insertion of secondary trocars into the abdomen is most safely performed under direct laparoscopic viewing.
Single-port surgery also has been described .
Figure 49-1.
Pregnant uterus at 10, 20, and 36 weeks’ gestation depicting distortion of other intraperitoneal organs.
Reproduced with permission from Kho KA: Diagnostic and operative laparoscopy.
In Yeomans ER, Hoffman BL, Gilstrap LC III, et al (eds): Cunningham and Gilstrap’s Operative Obstetrics, 3rd ed.
New York, NY: McGraw Hill; 2017.
Figure 49-2.
Hasson open entry technique for laparoscopic instrument placement.
A. Fascia grasped with two Allis clamps and elevated prior to sharp incision.
B. Two fascial stitches incorporate the peritoneum and fascia.
C. These fascial sutures are wrapped around holders of the Hasson cannula to anchor it in place.
Reproduced with permission from Kho KA: Diagnostic and operative laparoscopy.
In Yeomans ER, Hoffman BL, Gilstrap LC III, et al (eds): Cunningham and Gilstrap’s Operative Obstetrics, 3rd ed.
New York, NY: McGraw Hill; 2017.
In more advanced pregnancies, direct entry through a left upper quadrant port in the midclavicular line, 2 cm beneath the costal margin, may better avoid the fundus (Donkervoort, 2011; Stepp, 2004).
Known as the Palmer point, this entry site is also used in gynecological laparoscopy because visceroparietal adhesions infrequently form here .
Gasless laparoscopy is a less commonly selected alternative approach that uses a rod with intraabdominal fan-blade-shaped retractors.
When opened, these allow the abdominal wall to be lifted upward.
It avoids the typical laparoscopic cardiovascular changes because abdominal wall elevation is created by retraction rather than insufflation .
# Complications.
Risks inherent to any abdominal endoscopic procedure are probably slightly greater during pregnancy.
The obvious unique one is perforation of the pregnant uterus with a trocar or Veress needle (Kizer, 2011; Mala, 2014).
That said, reported complications are infrequent (Choi, 2021; Koo, 2012; Post, 2019).
# Perinatal Outcomes.
Perinatal outcomes in women are limited to observational studies.
Reedy and colleagues (1997) used the updated Swedish Birth Registry database to analyze a 20-year period with more than 2 million deliveries.
Of 2181 laparoscopic procedures, most were performed during the first trimester.
Perinatal outcomes for these women were compared with those of all women in the database and those undergoing open surgical procedures.
These investigators confirmed the earlier findings of an increased risk of low birthweight, preterm delivery, and fetal-growth restriction with surgery during pregnancy.
Differences were not found, however, in outcomes of women undergoing laparoscopy versus laparotomy.
An observational study of 262 women undergoing surgery for an adnexal mass noted similar findings .
Although the abortion and stillbirth rates are low with abdominal surgery, laparotomy has more adverse outcomes compared with laparoscopy .
Radiography.
Imaging modalities are used as adjuncts for diagnosis and therapy during pregnancy.
Options include sonography, radiography, computed tomography (CT), and magnetic resonance (MR) imaging.
Of these, radiography is the most problematic.
Inevitably, some radiographic procedures are performed before recognition of early pregnancy, usually because of trauma or serious illness .
Fortunately, most diagnostic radiographic procedures are associated with minimal fetal risks.
However, as with medications, these procedures may lead to a needless therapeutic abortion because of patient or physician anxiety or to litigation if pregnancy outcome is adverse.
The American College of Radiology (ACR) has addressed the growing concern of collective radiation doses in all fields of medicine .
More recent publications have been in support of FDA efforts to decrease radiation exposure and to reduce the number of unnecessary examinations.
Recommendations
also include considerations for radiosensitive populations, such as children and pregnant or potentially pregnant women.
At our institutions, special recommendations are made for gravidas.
Radiation exposure values and duration are recorded and monitored in high-exposure areas such as CT and fluoroscopy units.
Last, consultation with the radiologist is advised .
# Ionizing Radiation.
The term radiation refers to energy transmission and thus is applied to x-rays and also to microwaves, ultrasound, diathermy, and radio waves.
Of these, xrays and gamma rays have short wavelengths with very high energy and are ionizing radiation forms.
The other four energy forms have rather long wavelengths and low energy .
Ionizing radiation can directly damage DNA or can create free hydroxyl radicals that in turn damage DNA (Hall, 1991; National Research Council, 1990).
Methods of measuring the effects of x-rays are summarized in Table 49-5.
The standard terms used are exposure (in air), dose (to tissue), and relative effective dose (to tissue accounting for biological effects).
In the range of energies for diagnostic x-rays, the dose is now expressed in grays (Gy), and the relative effective dose is expressed in sieverts (Sv).
These can be used interchangeably.
For consistency, all doses discussed subsequently are expressed in currently used units of gray (1 Gy = 100 rad) or sievert (1 Sv = 100 rem).
To convert, 1 Sv = 100 rem = 100 rad. Table 49-5.
Some Measures of Ionizing Radiation As noted, x- and gamma-radiation at high doses can damage DNA, and this yields two biological effects in the fetus .
These are deterministic effects and stochastic effects.
# Deterministic Effects.
One potential harm of radiation exposure is deterministic, which may result in abortion, growth restriction, congenital malformations, or intellectual disability.
These deterministic effects are threshold effects, and the threshold level is the NOAEL—no observed adverse effect level .
Although controversial, the NOAEL concept supports that there is no risk below the threshold dose of 0.05 Gy or 5 rad.
It also suggests that the threshold for gross fetal malformations is more likely to be 0.2 Gy (20 rad) .
The deterministic effects of ionizing radiation have been extensively studied for cell damage that leads to disordered embryogenesis.
These have been assessed in animal models as well as in Japanese atomic bomb survivors and the Oxford Survey of Childhood Cancers .
Other sources have confirmed prior observations and provide additional information .
Animal Studies In the mouse model, the lethality risk is highest during the preimplantation period, which extends up to 10 days postconception .
Blastomere destruction caused by chromosomal damage is the likely cause .
During organogenesis, high-dose radiation—1 Gy or 100 rad—is more likely to cause malformations and growth restriction and less likely to be lethal.
Studies of brain development suggest effects on neuronal development and a window of cortical sensitivity in early and midfetal periods.
Instead, acute low-dose ionizing radiation appears to have no deleterious effects .
Human Data Data on adverse human effects of high-dose ionizing radiation mostly derive from the atomic bomb survivors of Hiroshima and Nagasaki (Greskovich, 2000; Otake, 1987).
The International Commission on Radiological Protection (2003) confirmed initial studies showing that the risk of severe intellectual disability was greatest between 8 and 15 weeks’ gestation .
The mean decrease in intelligence quotient (IQ) scores was 25 points per Gy or 100 rad.
The dose response appears linear, but it is unclear whether there is a threshold dose.
At 25 weeks’ gestation, a higher risk of intellectual disability in humans has not been documented, even with doses exceeding 0.5 Gy or 50 rad .
Most estimates err on the conservative side by assuming a linear nonthreshold hypothesis.
In a study of fetuses exposed to a low radiation dose in the first trimester, Guilbaud and colleagues (2019) did not find an increased risk
for miscarriage, congenital anomalies, or fetal-growth restriction.
Table 49-6.
Deterministic Effects of Ionizing Radiation in Pregnancy Reports have described high-dose radiation used to treat women for malignancy, menorrhagia, and uterine myomas.
Dekaban (1968) described 22 infants with microcephaly, intellectual disability, or both following exposure in the first half of pregnancy to an estimated 2.5 Gy or 250 rad for therapeutic radiation.
These doses are also carcinogenic for the fetus .
Summary of Fetal Radiation Exposure From 8 to 15 weeks’ gestation, the fetus is most susceptible to radiationinduced intellectual disability .
Whether this is a threshold or nonthreshold linear function of dose is unresolved.
The Committee on Biological Effects (1990) estimates the risk of severe intellectual disability to be as low as 4 percent for 0.1 Gy (10 rad) and as high as 60 percent for 1.5 Gy (150 rad).
Recall that these doses are 2 to 100 times higher than those considered maximal from diagnostic radiation.
Importantly, cumulative doses from multiple procedures may reach the harmful range, especially at 8 to 15 weeks’ gestation.
At 16 to 25 weeks’ gestation, the risk is less, and there is no proven risk before 8 weeks or after 25 weeks .
Embryofetal risks from low-dose diagnostic radiation appear to be minimal.
Current evidence suggests that risks for malformations, growth restriction, or spontaneous abortion are not increased from a radiation dose of less than 0.05 Gy (5 rad).
Brent (2009) concluded that gross congenital malformation rates would not be greater with exposure to less than 0.2 Gy (20 rad).
Diagnostic radiographs seldom exceed 0.1 Gy (10 rad) and thus, these procedures are unlikely to cause deterministic effects .
As emphasized by Groen and coworkers (2012), 0.1 Gy is the radiation equivalent to that from more than 1000 chest x-rays.
# Stochastic Effects.
These effects refer to random, presumably unpredictable oncogenic or mutagenic effects of radiation exposure.
Stochastic effects concern associations between fetal diagnostic radiation exposure and increased risk of childhood cancers or genetic diseases.
Excess cancers can result from in utero exposure to doses as low as 0.01 Sv or 1 rad (Doll, 1997; National Research Council, 2006).
The estimated risk of childhood cancer following fetal exposure to 0.03 Gy or 3 rad doubles the background risk of 1 cancer in 600 exposed fetuses to that of 2 in 600 .
In one report, in utero radiation exposure was linked to 10 solid cancers in adults from age 17 to 45 years.
There was a dose-response relationship as previously noted at the 0.1 Sv or 10 rem threshold.
These cancers likely are associated with a complex series of interactions between DNA and ionizing radiation.
These interactions make it more problematic to predict cancer risk from low-dose radiation of less than 10 rem.
Importantly, below doses of 0.1 to 0.2 Sv, evidence of a carcinogenic effect is not convincing (Brent, 2009, 2014; Preston, 2008; Strzelczyk, 2007).
# X-Ray Dosimetry.
Estimates of dose to the uterus and embryo for various frequently used radiographic examinations are summarized in Table 49-7.
Imaging of maternal body parts farthest from the uterus results in a very small dose of radiation scatter to the embryo or fetus.
The size of the woman, radiographic technique, and equipment performance are other variables .
Thus, data in the table serve only as guidelines.
When the radiation dose for a specific individual is required, a medical physicist should be consulted.
The Health Physics Society lists answers to questions commonly asked by patients .
Table 49-7.
Dose to the Uterus for Common Radiologic Procedures # Therapeutic Radiation.
The Radiation Therapy Committee Task Group of the American Association of Physics in Medicine emphasizes careful individualization of cancer radiotherapy for the pregnant woman .
In some cases, shielding of the fetus and other safeguards can be employed (Fenig, 2001; Nuyttens, 2002).
However, in other instances, the fetus will be exposed to dangerous
radiation doses, and a carefully designed plan must be improvised .
Models that estimate the fetal dose given during maternal brain radiotherapy or tangential breast irradiation have been developed .
The adverse pregnancy outcomes that occur years after abdominopelvic radiotherapy are detailed in Chapter 66 (p. 1164).
Brent, 2015; Wo, 2009).
# Diagnostic Radiation.
Radiographs To estimate fetal risk, approximate x-ray dosimetry must be known.
According to the American College of Radiology, no single diagnostic procedure results in a radiation dose significant enough to threaten embryofetal well-being .
For standard radiographs, dosimetry is presented in Table 49-7.
In pregnancy, the anterior-posterior-view chest radiograph is the most common study, and fetal exposure is exceptionally small—0.0007 Gy or 70 mrad.
The dose with one abdominal radiograph is higher—0.001 Gy or 100 mrad— because the embryo or fetus lies directly in the x-ray beam path.
The standard intravenous pyelogram may exceed 0.005 Gy or 500 mrad because of several exposures.
The one-shot pyelogram described in Chapter 56 (p. 999) is useful when urolithiasis or other causes of urinary tract obstruction are unproven by sonography.
Mammography and most “trauma series” radiographs of an extremity, skull, or rib deliver low doses because of distance from the fetus (Cepeda-Martins, 2021; Shakerian, 2015).
Fluoroscopy and Angiography Dosimetry calculations are much more difficult with these procedures because of variations in the number of radiographs obtained, total fluoroscopy time, and fluoroscopy time during which the fetus lies in the radiation field.
As shown in Table 49-8, the range varies.
Although the FDA limits the exposure rate for conventional fluoroscopy such as barium studies, special-purpose systems such as angiography units have the potential for much higher exposure.
Table 49-8.
Estimated X-Ray Doses to the Uterus/Embryo from Common Fluoroscopic Procedures Angiography and vascular embolization may occasionally be necessary for trauma and for serious maternal disorders.
As before, a greater distance from the embryo or fetus lowers the exposure and risk.
Computed Tomography In a recent report describing nearly 3.5 million pregnancies, the use of CT imaging from 1996 to 2016 increased fivefold .
These studies are usually performed by obtaining a spiral of 360-degree images that are postprocessed in multiple planes.
Of these, the axial image remains the most frequently obtained.
Multidetector CT (MDCT) images are now standard for common clinical indications.
The most recent detectors have more channels, and these multidetector protocols may result in higher dosimetry compared with prior CT imaging techniques.
Several imaging parameters have an effect on exposure .
These include pitch, kilovoltage, tube current, collimation, slice number, tube rotation, and total acquisition time.
If a study is performed with and without contrast, the dose is doubled because twice as many images are obtained.
Fetal exposure also varies with maternal size and fetal size and position.
As with plain radiography, the closer the target area is to the fetus, the greater the delivered dose.
Cranial CT imaging for evaluation of neurological disorders and eclampsia is the most frequently performed CT study in gravidas (Chaps.
41, p. 718 and 63, p. 1126).
Nonenhanced CT scanning is often used to detect acute hemorrhage within the epidural, subdural, or subarachnoid spaces .
Radiation dosage is negligible because of distance from the fetus .
Figure 49-3.
An image from a noncontrast computed tomography head study demonstrates a large right-sided frontoparietal temporal intraparenchymal hematoma (H ).
The midline (arrow) is shifted to the left due to mass effect from the hematoma.
Reproduced with permission from Dr. Amanda Zofkie.
Abdominal procedures are more problematic.
Hurwitz and associates (2006) employed a 16-channel multidetector scanner to calculate fetal exposure at 0 and 3 months’ gestation using a phantom model.
Calculations were made for three
commonly requested procedures in pregnant women .
The study showed their pulmonary embolism protocol has the same dosimetry exposure as the ventilation-perfusion (V/Q) lung scan discussed subsequently.
Although the appendicitis protocol has the highest radiation exposure, it is very useful clinically when MR imaging is not available.
Using a greater pitch markedly decreases the dosimetry and yields a sensitivity of 92 percent, a specificity of 99 percent, and a negativepredictive value of 99 percent .
This is discussed further in Chapter 55 (p. 987).
For suspected urolithiasis, the multidetector-scan protocol is used if sonography is nondiagnostic.
White and coworkers (2007) identified urolithiasis in 13 of 20 women with gestations aged an average of 26 weeks.
Last, as shown in Figure 49-4, abdominal tomography is performed if indicated in the pregnant woman with severe trauma (Herfel, 2018; Shakerian, 2015).
Table 49-9.
Estimated Radiation Dosimetry with 16-Channel Multidetector Computed-Tomographic (MDCT) Imaging Protocols Figure 49-4.
This woman in her third trimester was involved in a high-speed motor vehicle accident.
A. Maximum intensity projection acquired for maternal indications readily identifies fetal skull fractures (arrows).
B. 3-D reformatted CT image in a bone algorithm demonstrates the fetal skeleton from data acquired during the maternal examination.
Again, the arrow marks one fracture site.
Reproduced with permission from Bailey AA, Twickler DM: Perioperative imaging.
In Yeomans ER, Hoffman BL, Gilstrap LC III, et al (eds): Cunningham and Gilstrap’s Operative Obstetrics, 3rd ed.
New York, NY: McGraw Hill; 2017.
Photo contributor: Dr. Travis Browning.
Most experience with chest CT imaging is with cases of suspected pulmonary embolism.
Historically, pulmonary scintigraphy—the V/Q scan— was recommended for pregnant women by 70 percent of radiologists and chest CT angiography by 30 percent .
However, most currently agree that multidetector-CT pulmonary angiography (CTPA) has improved accuracy because of increasingly faster acquisition times .
Despite advances in technology, scintigraphy is still recommended by the American Thoracic Society for gravidas with a normal chest x-ray .
A higher use rate for CTPA has been reported, and dosimetry similar to that with V/Q scintigraphy has been emphasized (Brenner, 2007; Greer, 2015; Tromeur, 2019).
The rapid turnaround time with current CTPA protocols at most hospitals has advanced its selection as the preferred modality .
The algorithm in the YEARS study describes the use of D-dimer values and clinical criteria to define a subgroup of gravidas warranting further imaging.
Thus, the number of indicated CTPA studies resulting from this algorithm is markedly reduced (van der Pol, 2019).
In pregnancy, although a negative D-dimer test is helpful, these levels may be normally elevated with increasing gestation and certain maternal complications .
Of other aspects in study selection, the fetal radiation doses are lower with CT pulmonary angiography (CTPA) compared with the V/Q scan.
However, maternal chest radiation doses are substantially higher with CTPA (van Mens, 2017).
The most recent ongoing Optimised Computed Tomography Pulmonary Angiography in Pregnancy Quality and Safety (OPTICA) study is a prospective trial using a uniform low-dose CTPA protocol to enable definitive recommendations.
Until results are known, our reduced-exposure CTPA protocol is recommended as the initial preferred imaging modality in suspected pulmonary embolism .
CT pelvimetry is used by some before attempting breech vaginal delivery .
The fetal dose approaches 0.015 Gy or 1.5 rad, but use of a low-exposure technique may reduce this to 0.0025 Gy or 0.25 rad.
Radiographic Contrast Agents These can be given intravenously or taken orally.
Intravenous contrast agents are considered category B by the FDA.
These agents are iodinated and of low osmolality, and thus they cross the placenta to the fetus.
With watersoluble iodinated contrast, no cases of neonatal hypothyroidism or other adverse
effects have been documented .
Oral contrast preparations, typically containing iodine or barium, have minimal systemic absorption, and are unlikely to affect the fetus.
Nuclear Medicine Studies These studies are performed by “tagging” a radioactive element to a carrier that can be injected, inhaled, or swallowed.
For example, the radioisotope technetium-99m (Tc-99m) may be tagged to red blood cells, sulfur colloid, or pertechnetate.
The method used to tag the agent determines fetal radiation exposure.
The amount of placental transfer is obviously important, but maternal renal clearance is also factored because of fetal proximity to her bladder.
Measurement of radioactive technetium is based on its decay, and the units used are the curie (Ci) or the Becquerel (Bq).
Dosimetry is usually expressed in millicuries (mCi).
The effective tissue dose is expressed in sievert units (Sv) with conversion of 1 Sv = 100 rem = 100 rad .
Depending on the physical and biochemical properties of a radioisotope, an average fetal exposure can be calculated (Wagner, 1997; Zanzonico, 2000).
Commonly used radiopharmaceuticals and estimated absorbed fetal doses are given in Table 49-10.
The radionuclide dose should be kept as low as possible .
Exposures vary with gestational age and are greatest earlier in pregnancy for most radiopharmaceuticals.
One exception is the later effect of iodine-131 on the fetal thyroid .
Table 49-10.
Radiopharmaceuticals Used in Nuclear Medicine Studies In a V/Q scan, perfusion is measured with injected Tc-99m macroaggregated albumin, and ventilation is measured with inhaled xenon127 or xenon-133.
Fetal exposure with either is negligible (Chan, 2002; Mountford, 1997).
Thyroid scanning with iodine-123 or iodine-131 seldom is indicated in pregnancy.
However, with the trace diagnostic doses used, fetal risk is minimal.
In contrast, therapeutic doses of radioiodine to treat maternal Graves disease or thyroid cancer may cause fetal thyroid ablation and cretinism.
The sentinel lymphoscintigram is a commonly used preoperative study in nonpregnant women to detect the axillary lymph node most likely to have metastases from breast cancer.
Tc-99m–sulfur colloid is used in this diagnostic study (Newman, 2007; Spanheimer, 2009).
The calculated dose approximates 0.014 mSv or 1.4 mrad, which should not preclude its safe use during pregnancy.
Sonography.
The development of sonography for study of the fetus and mother is one of the greater achievements in obstetrics.
The technique has become virtually indispensable in everyday practice.
Its wide-ranging clinical uses are further discussed in Chapters 14 and 15 and in other sections of this book.
Magnetic Resonance Imaging.
Magnetic resonance technology does not use ionizing radiation, and its use in pregnancy is constantly evolving (Gopireddy, 2021; Mervak, 2019).
Advantages include sharp resolution at soft-tissue interfaces, ability to characterize tissue composition, and acquisition of images in any plane— particularly axial, sagittal, and coronal.
A portion of Chapter 14 (p. 263) is devoted to mechanisms that generate MR images, and imaging examples are provided throughout this book.
# Safety.
The update of the expert panel on MR safety of the ACR was summarized by Kanal and colleagues (2013).
The panel concluded that no harmful human effects are reported from MR imaging.
Similar conclusions were reached by the International Society for Ultrasound in Obstetrics and Gynecology (2017).
When operated within standardized limits, maternal and fetal imaging can be safely performed at clinical magnet strengths—3 tesla (T) and below.
MR imaging can be used regardless of trimester: (1) if the information cannot be obtained with another nonionizing modality, namely sonography; (2) if the study results will guide maternal or fetal management during pregnancy; and (3) if the imaging cannot be delayed until the woman is no longer pregnant.
The decision to use a magnetic field strength >1.5 T may be made for specific maternal indications.
Early work also suggests imaging at 3 T
is safe and it improves fetal assessment (Chartier, 2019; Victoria, 2016).
No demonstrable fetal heart rate pattern changes occur during MR imaging of gravidas .
Last, studies evaluating children exposed in utero have shown no deleterious effects (Kok, 2004; Reeves, 2010).
Contraindications to MR imaging include internal cardiac pacemakers, neurostimulators, implanted defibrillators and infusion pumps, cochlear implants, shrapnel or other metal in biologically sensitive areas, some intracranial aneurysm clips, and any metallic foreign body in the eye.
Of more than 51,000 nonpregnant patients scheduled for MR imaging, one study found that only 0.4 percent had an absolute contraindication to the procedure .
# Contrast Agents.
Several different elemental gadolinium chelates are used to create paramagnetic contrast.
These cross the placenta and are found in the fetus and placenta and are concentrated in amnionic fluid .
In doses approximately 10 times the normal human dose, a gadolinium-based contrast agent caused slight developmental delay in rabbit fetuses.
Inadvertant fetal exposure usually occurs in early pregnancy .
The American College of Radiology cites a study of 26 women given a gadolinium derivative in the first trimester without adverse fetal effects .
Despite this, routine use of gadolinium is not recommended unless potential benefits outweigh fetal risks (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2017; American College of Radiology, 2020; Briggs, 2017).
This recommendation stems from a possible dissociation of the toxic gadolinium ion from its ligand within amnionic fluid and thus potential prolonged exposure of the fetus.
# Maternal Indications.
In some cases, MR imaging may complement CT, and in others, MR imaging is preferable .
MR imaging is also a superb tool to evaluate the maternal abdomen and retroperitoneal space.
One example is evaluation of right lower quadrant pain in pregnancy, specifically with suspected appendicitis (Aguilera, 2018; Tsai, 2017).
It can aid detection and localization of adrenal, renal, and gastrointestinal lesions as well as pelvic masses in pregnancy (Boyd, 2012; Raj, 2020; Tica, 2013).
Maternal central nervous system abnormalities, such as brain tumors or spinal trauma, are more clearly seen with MR imaging.
This makes it invaluable in the diagnosis of neurological emergencies .
Other modalities include MR urography for renal urolithiasis and cardiac MR for investigating normal physiology, complex defects, and cardiomyopathies (Mullins, 2012; Nelson, 2015; Stewart, 2016).
The application of cardiovascular MR imaging in pregnant women is expanding .
MR imaging helps also evaluate many pregnancy-specific disorders.
It is chosen by many to determine the degree and extent of invasion in placenta accreta spectrum .
As discussed in Chapter 40 (p. 701), MR imaging has provided important insights into the pathophysiology of preeclampsia (Nelander, 2018; Zeeman, 2014).
As discussed in Chapter 37 (p. 656), CT and MR imaging are useful for puerperal infection evaluation, but MR imaging provides better visualization of the bladder flap area following cesarean delivery (Brown, 1999; Twickler, 1997).
Last, preliminary studies of placental function with MR imaging are promising .
# Fetal Indications.
Fetal MR imaging provides a complement to sonography (Laifer-Narin, 2007; Sandrasegaran, 2006).
According to Zaretsky and associates (2003a), MR imaging can be used to display almost all elements of the standard fetal anatomical survey.
Moreover, the quality of three-dimensional anatomical reconstruction with MR fetal imaging is superb .
The most frequent fetal indications are evaluation of complex abnormalities of the brain, chest, and genitourinary systems .
Reichel (2003) and Twickler (2002) and their colleagues have validated its use for fetal central nervous system anomalies and biometry .
Others have described MR imaging of fetuses with suprarenal masses or with renal anomalies and oligohydramnios (Castro, 2019; Hawkins, 2008).
Fetal weight estimation may be more accurate with MR
imaging than with sonography (Kadji, 2019; Zaretsky, 2003b).
And MR imaging has been shown to accurately identify fetal anemia requiring transfusions (Jørgensen, 2019).
Figure 49-5.
Nullipara with a 27 weeks’ gestation.
A. Axial T2-weighted MR image shows mild fetal unilateral ventriculomegaly involving the left lateral ventricle (arrow).
B. Sagittal T2-weighted MR image demonstrates normal development of the corpus callosum (arrowheads) and vermis (arrow).
Fetal movement is problematic for MR imaging, but faster acquisitions eliminate the problem.
Morphology is primarily assessed with fast T2weighted sequences such as half-Fourier acquisition single shot turbo spin echo (HASTE) or single shot fast spin echo (SSFSE).
Fetal indications and findings of MR imaging are discussed more extensively in Chapter 14 (p. 266) and throughout this book.
Imaging During Pregnancy.
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2017) has reviewed the effects of radiographic, sonographic, and magnetic-resonance exposure during pregnancy.
Its suggested guidelines are shown in Table 4911.
Table 49-11.
Guidelines for Diagnostic Imaging During Pregnancy and Lactation